<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>will chan's random blog</title>
 <link href="http://http://williamchan.github.io//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://http://williamchan.github.io//"/>
 <updated>2015-07-01T03:22:40-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://http://williamchan.github.io/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Will Chan</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Ditch the annual review</title>
   <link href="http://http://williamchan.github.io//2015/07/01/ditch-the-annual-review/"/>
   <updated>2015-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://http://williamchan.github.io//2015/07/01/ditch-the-annual-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Annual reviews are dreaded and hated by many, even when they are conducted by well-intentioned and kind teammates. Here’s what is wrong with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They are awful mechanisms for feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: Did up to 12 months really have to pass for that piece of constructive criticism to be made known? Couldn’t we celebrate our colleagues’ wins at team events along the way? Write me up for anything I did more than 5 weeks ago and I can hardly confirm nor deny, which hinders my constructive response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Witch-hunts for weaknesses&lt;/strong&gt;: Reviews tend to devolve into witch-hunts for weaknesses. This can happen even with the most supportive of work environments. Maybe your closest friends at the office write great positive feedback about your performance over the last 12 months (again, lol), plus a single “thing to improve.” Guess which details your manager will clue into?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some wizard-level engineers. Even they have weaknesses, but do you think that nitpicking on their perceived weaknesses will necessarily make them better at what they do? Honestly not. If anything, they should be encouraged to become even more of who they are. Great work is often not done by well-rounded people with few weaknesses but by brilliant weirdos with (hopefully adorable) weaknesses. To put it in terms of economics, this is called developing your &lt;em&gt;competitive advantage&lt;/em&gt;. In terms of Maslow’s hierarchy, this is called &lt;em&gt;self-actualization&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subjectivity of reviews introduce compensation disparity&lt;/strong&gt;: In &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt;, the Oakland A’s used objective metrics to combat the subjectivity of individual scouts. Even with the best talent scouts in the world, there is no getting around the fact that it requires LOTS of observation to even notice whether a player is batting .200 or .300 (which in baseball is a big difference). In many professions, there is no easy, statistical way to measure our effectiveness, and our reviews are often limited to anecdotal and subjective observations. When such anecdotes are used to set raises and compensation, that really creates problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones who receive raises are often the best at communicating their accomplishments, attracting the attention of management, and asking for raises. I would bet money that this dynamic is at least partly responsible for the wage disparity between men and women in many industries including technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would like is to find a better solution to these age-old management problems. It begins with fostering healthy feedback between teammates — those are the table stakes. Please do not wait up to 12 months to show appreciation or suggest a change in behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, mitigate the role of subjectivity in compensation. The legal profession offers a practical model: 1st-years make X and 4th-years make Y, no questions asked. Meritocracy is enforced by the partner track, a long-term evaluation for leadership — you know when you’re on it, and you know when you’re not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply this in the tech industry, for example, set salaries based on years of experience per role (competitive with the market, of course). A “staff engineer” marches up a compensation matrix every year until that employee receives a promotion. Call it a zero-salary band for each role-and-rank. This reduces the freedom to outbid competing offers on the basis of salary when trying to recruit a promising candidate. But the company can strongly signal that it values its employees and that promotions come to those who display undeniable long-term leadership, such as authoring tools that become widely adopted, hiring tons of great people, or building out a thriving business group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;em&gt;personalize&lt;/em&gt; career goals to the employee. Do not assume that all employees have similar goals. For some, success could mean delivering well-attended conference talks. Others could have aspirations to start companies in the future and want to be staffed on projects that involve fast iteration. Managers who understand and support their employees’ career goals will have better luck retaining their teams and keeping them motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to that a communicative work environment without antiquated management rituals such as status quo-style reviews. I would want to work at such a company.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Elon Musk biography - on aggressive learning and a fantastic future</title>
   <link href="http://http://williamchan.github.io//2015/06/16/elon-musk-biography/"/>
   <updated>2015-06-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://http://williamchan.github.io//2015/06/16/elon-musk-biography</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What can I say, call me a Musk fanboy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Elon-Musk-SpaceX-Fantastic-Future/dp/0062301233&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elon Musk: Tesla, SpaceX, and the Quest for a Fantastic Future&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. What an inspirational book! It has taught me several lessons about the business of technology while provoking much self-reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Time to hit the books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in the book, Elon is quoted as saying &amp;quot;I think there are probably too many smart people pursuing Internet stuff, finance, and law.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made me &lt;em&gt;gulp&lt;/em&gt;. A decade ago, I turned my back on finance and law so that I could be a productive web programming member of society. The idea that &amp;quot;Internet stuff&amp;quot; can be grouped together with finance and law in societal value made me think about my place in the world. He hit me again toward the end of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You should have a pretty broad engineering and scientific background.... Engineers are usually trained in a very fixed area. When you&amp;#39;re able to think about all of these disciplines together, you kind of think differently and can dream of much crazier things and how they might work.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My strengths include progamming, math, and finance. The confidence I had drawn from these areas of expertise melted away. Truth be told, I had already began making plans to update my skills in preparation for the next wave of innovation. (Coursera is amazing.) The writing is on the walls: the days of easy innovation in cloud-based software are nearing an end. Meanwhile, the barrier to entry for web and mobile programming nowadays is essentially nil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading Musk caution against having &amp;quot;fixed area&amp;quot; engineering backgrounds has abruptly moved up my self-learning timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it inspiring to remember that Musk post-PayPal had essentially the same technical skillset that I do now: web software. He learned about rocket science, battery engineering, solar panels, and car manufacturing by reading and talking to people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have ordered several textbooks in adjacent disciplines such as robotics, machine learning, and physics. It&amp;#39;s time to double-down on training up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On engineering risk-taking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;SpaceX had been making significant changes to its rocket since the last, failed launch. A traditional aerospace company would not have wanted the added risk, but Musk insisted that SpaceX push its technology forward while at the same time trying to make it work right.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace &amp;quot;traditional aerospace company&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;career software engineers&amp;quot; and you essentially have described the kind of well-intentioned, &amp;quot;senior&amp;quot; programmer that much of the industry produces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My blood must still be running hot because I feel like it&amp;#39;s time to take the gloves off and take some bold engineering risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On SpaceX culture breaking the corporate mold&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Make sure your output is high,&amp;quot; [SpaceX president Gwynne] Shotwell said. &amp;quot;If we&amp;#39;re throwing a bunch of shit in your way, you need to be mouthy about it. That&amp;#39;s not a quality that&amp;#39;s widely accepted elsewhere, but it is at SpaceX.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely does not sound like my father&amp;#39;s Rocketdyne/Boeing/UTX!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On SolarCity&amp;#39;s gameplan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember two things about solar panels in the last decade: that they were difficult to install and that their prices kept dropping. It was against this backdrop that SolarCity executed its business plan: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;At the time, it was not easy for consumers to get solar panels on their houses. You had to be very proactive, acquiring the panels and finding someone else to install them. The consumer paid up front and had to make an educated guess as to whether or not his or her house even got enough sunshine to make the ordeal worthwhile. On top of all this people were reluctant to buy panels, knowing that the next year&amp;#39;s models would be more efficient.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it has been pointed out, how obvious it seems that homeowners do not want to invest in rapidly changing solar panel technology, and that a business innovation could make such concerns disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On the brilliance of the Gigafactory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The Gigafactory is Tesla&amp;#39;s lithium-ion battery factory.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The competitors... think it&amp;#39;s a stupid idea, that the battery supplier should just go build something like that. But I know the idea of spending several billion dollars on a battery factory. You&amp;#39;ve got a chicken-and-egg problem where the car companies are not going to commit to a giant volume because they&amp;#39;re not sure you can sell enough electric cars.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, no other car company is making anywhere near the kinds of investments in battery production. It will be amusing to watch from afar how things play out for those competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mongo+Kerberos - documentation matters</title>
   <link href="http://http://williamchan.github.io//2015/04/20/mongo-kerberos-documentation-matters/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://http://williamchan.github.io//2015/04/20/mongo-kerberos-documentation-matters</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;By far the most painful work project of this year has been connecting the Paxata application to a Kerberos-protected Mongo database. I have come to the conclusion that if Kerberos is involved, then prepare for suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish that the moral of this story was that I never give up on a technical challenge, but really I was saved by the patience of some really awesome people at Mongo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerberos_(protocol)&quot;&gt;Kerberos&lt;/a&gt; is an authentication protocol that uses private keys, aka shared secrets, to secure computing resources and services. Shared secrets are really great for securing things, but in many cases, securely distributing those secrets is a showstopper because of the risk that those secrets are unsecurely transmitted. In a Kerberos environment, a trusted administrator configures those shared secrets within a closed computer network. (Think VP of IT at a large corporation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My devops coworker and I started work on this project by setting up a Mongo Enterprise server with a Kerberos client. Then the headwalling began as we tried unsuccessfully to connect to Kerberos-enabled Mongo from a command line. For 2-3 weeks, we double-checked the available documentation, puzzled over cryptic error messages, and exhaustively tested hypotheses. It wore me out to the point that I focused on other projects at work for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reengaged a few weeks later when I attended a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/San-Francisco-MongoDB-User-Group/events/220789385/&quot;&gt;fascinating talk about Mongo version 3.0&lt;/a&gt; that touched on details about the inner workings of databases and distributed computing. From there, I connected with a Kerberos expert at Mongo who was willing to provide back-and-forth email support until I succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two major issues. The first, which had to do with logging into a Kerberos-enabled Mongo from a command line, ended up being a case where the documented example showed an incorrect approach. The second major hurdle encountered was that the Paxata application would not connect to that same database. The issue here ended up being... drumroll... quotations (&amp;quot;yes&amp;quot; &amp;quot;these&amp;quot; &amp;quot;things&amp;quot;) around some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_Authentication_and_Authorization_Service&quot;&gt;JAAS configs&lt;/a&gt;. Amount of illustrative documentation on the internet = zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can release a product to on-prem customers with confidence that they can use it with Kerberos-protected Mongo databases. I will prepare some documentation on how to set this up end-to-end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe someday I can get back to work that looks more like computer science. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
